<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The ryght and trew vndersta[n]dynge of the Supper of the Lord and the vse therof faythfully gathered out of ye holy Scriptures worthely to be embrased of all Christen people. Perused [and] alowed by dyuerse godly lerned men to the comfort of al ye trewe congregation of Christ.</title>
            <author>Lancaster, Thomas, d. 1583.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1550</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 83 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 44 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A05045</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15188</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S108242</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843914</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843914</idno>
            <idno type="VID">8679</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A05045)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8679)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 103:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The ryght and trew vndersta[n]dynge of the Supper of the Lord and the vse therof faythfully gathered out of ye holy Scriptures worthely to be embrased of all Christen people. Perused [and] alowed by dyuerse godly lerned men to the comfort of al ye trewe congregation of Christ.</title>
                  <author>Lancaster, Thomas, d. 1583.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[88] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By [E. Whitechurch? for] Iohan Turke],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprynded [sic] at Londone :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1550?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication and ostensible printer's name colophon; actual printer's name and publication date conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E F⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:8679:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8679:1"/>
            <p>¶ The ryght and trew vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge of the Supper of the Lord and the vſe ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of faythfully gathered out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy Scriptures wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thely to be embraſed of all Chriſten people.</p>
            <p>Peruſed &amp; alowed by dyuerſe godly lerned men to the comfort of al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> trewe congregation of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>¶Beati qui ad cenam nuptiarum agni vocati ſunt. Apo .xix.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:8679:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8679:2"/>
            <head>¶To the moſt pueſaunt &amp; myghty Prince Edward the .vi. by the grace of God Kynge of England, Fraunce and Ireland, defender of the fayth, and of the Churche of England and alſo of Ireland in earth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſupreme head: your moſt humble &amp; obediente Seruaunte Thomas Lancaſter hartely wyſhith all grace and peace fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> god with longe Reigne, honor, helthe and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperite.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Race be w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtye and peace from god our father &amp; from our Lord Ieſus chriſt Amen. And it pleaſe your Maieſte for this cauſe haue I dedicate this my ſimple laboure vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your grace. Fyrſt becauſe I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god hathe called your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie to be apreferrer of his holi and bleſſed worde as by another Ioſias whiche Lord of power proſper your moſt excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Maieſtie in al your di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uine
<pb facs="tcp:8679:3"/>
affayres &amp; godly enterpriſes Secondarily becauſe ther is found many diuers ſectes vnder Chriſtes name at thys preaſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te, as Papiſtes Lutherians, Swynglia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtes, Laudia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> other mo, lyke as ther was among y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes, as Haſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butri Hemero. Baptiſta, Eſſei, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducei Phareſei. &amp;c. And euery one of them boſtid the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the lordes word, &amp; wold be Chriſtians, althought y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the moſt parte of theſe fore reherſed ſec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, hath not reaceauyd nether word nor ſprit nor no chriſtian lerninge, &amp; therfore ar they ſo ready to perſecute them that hath the word ſprite &amp; life, but what helpes it, it hath bene thus from the begynnyng, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſpiritual chyldryn of God muſte ſuffer of the fleſhelye, as Abell of Caine, Iſaac of Iſmaell, Iacob of Eſau and the ſpiritual chyldren of Iſraell of the fleſhely. For before it pleaſed God to reſtore in to thys Realme (by youre
<pb facs="tcp:8679:3"/>
graces moſt noble father, and nowe by your maieſtie) the Goſpel &amp; Ioy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full tydinges of hys dearly beloued ſonne our ſauyor Ieſu Chryſt, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidelytie as chefe Ruler reyngned in our hartes, Hipocriſie as a vayne glorious Empereſſe beare dominio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſuperſtition, Idolatrye, falſe ſectes, mens traditions, confidens repoſed in mens inuentions, Pilgrimages, offerynges, Bulles, Pardons, Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſations, Maſſes, marchaundice for merites and workes, bieng &amp; ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge of the deuine miſteres, wyth other abhomenable baggage more, was crept into the great diſquietnes of thys your holy Chatholike Chur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, but without doubte they ſhal no longer preuayle for the daye of the Lorde is at hand which ſhal breke Sata<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s heed and deſtroy both him and al his miniſters wyth the breathe of his mouth. For he wil no longer ſuffer thys great wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
<pb facs="tcp:8679:4"/>
and abhomynacion, he wyll be knowen for the God and ſauyoure alone he is the Lorde whiche alone wylbe exalted and al Idoles ſhalbe vtterly bro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ken in peaces.<note place="margin">Eſaie .ii.</note> He is that God, whiche wyll no longer ſuffer hys glorye to be geuen to other. He is that lauer which wyl expulſe the darkenes of mens tradicions, that fyght wyth hys infallible veryte, &amp; brynge in the gloryous lyght of his moſt holy worde. To be ſhorte he wyll ouerthrowe all the Idollys y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> obſcure his glorye, and ſet vp hys blyſſed name to be prayſed for euer and euer Ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Of this his holy wyl haue we experyens eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at this tyme in whiche it hath pleſed hym to ſend vs your Maieſtie his derely belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ſeruaunte oure moſt vertuous lawful and godlye kynge to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorowe (not aparte) but all Anty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chryſtes kyngdome, by your diuine polecy and godly enterpryſes. So
<pb facs="tcp:8679:4"/>
that the greate hore of Babilon,<note place="margin">Apo. xvii.</note> the mother of all Hordome and abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minacions of the earth. Hath loſte her chefe glorye and renowne. And is nowe become ſo vyle, that ſhe is made the habytacion of Deuelles, &amp; the Holde of all fowle ſpyrites,<note place="margin">Apo. xviii. Eſaie .xii. Iore. xv Apo. xiiii. pſ. xiiii iiii Pſa. i.xvi</note> &amp; A cage of all vncleane and hathefull Byrdes, ſo that no man nowe wyll once by any of her marcha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des. And wythout doubte the time is (by god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des prouidence and your graces) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Babylon hath in this realme ſuche a faule, that it ſhall not after this tyme at any tyme be repaired. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mouth of the Lorde hath ſpoken it, whiche is faythfull in all his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, and whoſe truthe abideth for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer and euer, neyther can this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy of Chryſt by made fruſtrate by any humayne polyce. Euery plant y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> my heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly father hath not pla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted ſhalbe plucke vp by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rotes,<note place="margin">Math. xv.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:8679:5"/>
whoſo reioyſeth not to heare theſe thynges: yea who tryu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>phes not to ſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Bleſſed ar we your ſubiets to whom it hath chaunced not only to here theſe thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges Ioyfully, but alſo to ſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo plentyfully put in vre by your Maieſtie, ſo that al your faith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full ſubiectes beinge no papiſtes do faythfullye reioyſe. And although, we be occaſioned diuers wayſe to ge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue god immortal tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes for dyuers gyftes, yet we thynke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we are moſt hyghly bounde to be thankefull for the reſtitution of hys holy worde in thys your graces dayes. And woo worth them that be vnthankeful to hym in thys behalfe, &amp; diſobediente to your Maieſtie, except they repent and ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. Wherfore I deſyre your Maieſtie for the loue of god y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> your grace reade it and iudge it wyth the Lordes worde, &amp; cauſe it to be Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged of them that ar godly lerned, &amp; not of ſuſpected Papiſtes. And yf
<pb facs="tcp:8679:5"/>
they can confute it I wyl gladly be lerned. But &amp; I haue the truthe and not they. I deſire your grace for the tender mercy of god, and as ye wyll anſwer afore god at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> daye of Iud<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gement y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye wyl protecte &amp; defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de it acording to your office, &amp; that youre loui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ſubiectes becauſe of wekenes of the fleſhe be not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pelled to come from Chriſt to Antichriſt, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> truth to falſed, from euerlaſtynge lyfe to euerlaſting dethe. I knowe wel and it pleaſe your Maieſty y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ther ſhalbe kyckyng agaynſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prycke,<note place="margin">Eſay .xl.</note> notwith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding I paſſe not, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth may no lenger be hid,<note place="margin">i. Pet. i Eſay. xiiii Iude. i</note> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth may not come to nowght becauſe of the lye, gods word remaynes euerlaſtyng. Was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good Angels worſe becauſe of Lu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cifers prynde, what hyndreth it y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .xi. Appoſtles y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Iudas was a traytour euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall beare his owne bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyne, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father ſhal not beare y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryghtwyſnes of hys ſonne, nor the
<pb facs="tcp:8679:6"/>
ſonne the vnryghtwyſnes of his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. But the ſoule that ſinneth ſhal dye. Was the pure cleane lerning of the .xii. Apoſtles worſe that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> theyr was ſo manye damnable ſectes in theyr tyme vnder Chryſtes name? whiche ſectes were no leſſe then .vii. The fyrſt learned Circumſicion, the ſeconde that there was no reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyon, The thyrde as Philetus and Himeneus that the Reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was al paſt. The fourth that the daye of the Lord is at hande. The fyrte the Nicholaitans whiche hath had ther wyfes in comen. The ſyxte the Ebi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onytes that denyed the Godhed of Chryſt. The ſeuenth the corinthia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s whiche lerned ſuche abhomynable thynges, agaynſt whiche .ii. laſt ſec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes ſaynt Iohan did wryte his goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell and hys Epyſtles. Nowe ſeing this ineſtemable benefite of goddes word is ſo bounteouſly geuen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs. Let vs youre pore ſubiectes
<pb facs="tcp:8679:6"/>
all together conſent with one minde to conſerue &amp; mayntayne this moſt precyous Iewell that we loſe it not hereafter thorough oure owne ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glygences. Let vs not hinder your Maieſties procedi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boute to repayre and buyld agayne the Temple of oure Lord God, but rather further it y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you may haue a proſperous ſucceſſe, &amp; brynge youre laboure to a fortunate ende. In co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideracion wherof all though I am no fyt perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be a worckeman in this behalfe, yet verely I deſyre w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all my harte y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this buildi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g may go forward. And I wyſhe to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are vnder youre Maieſtie, all proſperous &amp; fortunate thynges, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they maye bring theyr worke to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectnes. And although I can not greatly furder there godly labours, yet wyl I not hynder the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but helpe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the vttremoſt of my power in al thinges. Let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bring Ceder tres
<pb facs="tcp:8679:7"/>
Syluer, Golde, Perle and precious ſtones to the byldynge. And garny<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhynge of this Temple. I wyll a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine with the poore wedowe in the Goſpell of Luke,<note place="margin">Luce. xii.</note> brynge into the treaſure houſe two Mytes, that is for my part, gather the ſtones, fetch the tember and make the morter, or do ſuche ſmall thinges as my lyttel ſtrenghes ſhalbe able to beare and ſuffer. And to thentent y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> your ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie maye haue an experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of my good wyl toward y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bylding of the temple. Behold at this tyme I ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue vnto your maieſty this my boke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I wold ſo gladly wer put in print yf it were lyſenced, wherein is decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the ryght inſtitucion and vſe of the ſupper of oure Lorde. And ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kewyſe deſcloſynge the abbomyna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Idolatrye and falſe vſyng of it. And to the intente that bothe the perſecuter and ſclanderer of goddes worde, maie know vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> what grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d
<pb facs="tcp:8679:7"/>
y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ryght congregacyon of Ieſus Chryſt the dearely beloued bryde, that holye Chryſten churche y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lyttyl flocke, to the whiche it pleaſed the father to gyue that kyngdome, and to thentent y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> your grace may know which of all theſe for reherſed ſectes is founde vpryght in the learninge of Ieſus Chryſt. For I ſaye vnto you in Chryſt Ieſu. Lyke as there was one Adam and Eua, one Noe and one Arke, one Iſaac and one Rebecca, one houſe of Iſraell, one Ieruſalem, &amp; one Te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple. So is ther one Chryſte and one congregacion, whych congregacion hath one Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, one fayth, one Baptyme, &amp; one Supper, one vpryght waye &amp; wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng to euerylaſtyng lyfe, acording to the declaracion of goddes worde. And al they that hath not theſe thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges afore reherſed. Namely Goſpel fayth, Baptime, Supper, waye and waylkynge, he is no member in the
<pb facs="tcp:8679:8"/>
congregation of god,<note place="margin">ii. Iohn .i.</note> here profiteth nother name nor fame, we muſt be founde inwardly and outwardelye in the lernyng of Ieſu Chriſt or we haue no god. Yt cold not helpe Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raell that they ware Abrams childe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryn &amp; had not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dedes of Abra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. viii</note> ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore examyne thys ſupper, &amp; ye ſhal finde it y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> right ſupper of Ieſu chriſt that euerlaſtyng word,<note place="margin">Iacob .i. Math. xvi Exo. i.xix.</note> that word of truthe, the worde of grace, the ſaffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makinge worde, that worde that is vnpoſſible to be ouercom. Yea y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ga<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes of hel ſhal not preuayle agaynſt it, it is the two edged ſworde that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myth out of the mouth of the lord it is the ſworde of the ſprite, and w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it ſhal he ſmite the hethen. Therfore our hope and truſt is in your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie for the buyldynge agayne of thys temple that is in decaye, &amp; that ye wyll not be lyke vnto theſe mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therars of ſayntes that hath byn in
<pb facs="tcp:8679:8"/>
tyme paſſed, which hath not ſtreuen agaynſte fleſhe and bloude, but agaynſt hym whoſe eyes is a flame of fyre, and in ryghtwyſnes doth he iudge and make battel, whiche is Crowned with manye Crownes, &amp; hys name no man knoweth, but he hym ſelfe, and hys veſture is depte in bloude, and hys name is called y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worde of God,<note place="margin">Apo. xix Pſalm. ii.</note> which ruleth the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then wyth arode of Iron, and tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the wyne, fat of ferſenes and wrathe of almyghty God, and hath on hys veſture and on hys thyghe a name wrytten kynge of all kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and Lorde of al Lordes. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I deſyre your grace that ye ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amyne wyth the Lordes worde this my pore boke. And by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> helpe of god your grace ſhal fynd nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ſought for, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prayſe of Ieſu Chryſt, the which he him ſelfe hath brought out of Heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, lerned w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his bleſſed mouth
<pb facs="tcp:8679:9"/>
and ſeled with his precyous bloud. Therefore my deſyre is to almygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty god the preſeruacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of your ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yeſtie, and that he wyll preſerue in you that newe and cleane harte and kepe open the eyes of youre vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandyng that ye may auoyde the vngodly counſelles of the ſhauen nacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that hathe brought this chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che in ſuche rewyne that your gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce hath muche to doo to repayre it agayne. I nede not to reſite ther fac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes nor ther names to your grace, ye knowe them wel enough they haue prycked at the kynges preuaye cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. The lord be bleſſed y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hath ſent vs ſuch a godlye kynge &amp; gracious gouerner to delyuer vs, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> morther Ieſus chriſt in his me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> power of death &amp; tyrantes handes, I wyll not ſaye that they are preuaye traytours, but thys is trwe they are preuey Idolaters, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſydes thys rewmour renneth into al
<pb facs="tcp:8679:9"/>
landes, that they haue cauſed the kynges maieſtie y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dede is (of whoſe ſoule the lorde haue mercy) to make ſuche lawes that no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> myght ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue nor rade the Goſpell but men of ſertayne degres and that poore men ſhulde be occupyed wyth fables, what ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be more blaſphemy agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt god and his anoynted Ieſus, then to depryue his members of his god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly worde, whiche lawes (bleſſed be god) is by your maieſtie aboliſhed. Theſe Antichryſtes haue alwayes defended ther cauſe with the ſword. But Chryſt Ieſus wyth mekenes and wyth hys holy worde. O bludy wrathe and wryched tyranny which goeth aboue the wrathe of al vnrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable creatures. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fearſe Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the ragyng Bere, and the gry, pi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g wolfe, is euer one of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at peace in there generacion. But theſe blud thruſty Dogges neuer faciate, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che ſhulde be made lyke vnto the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage
<pb facs="tcp:8679:10"/>
of God, which is borne w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> out tethe, nayles &amp; horne, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> feble tender fleſh without wyt ſpeche or myght, whiche can neyther go nor ſtande, which alonely muſt lyue by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> helpe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pore mother, in a token y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he is a creatur of peace, he is ſo ful of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les ſo ful of blud, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can think nor write. O how wide ar y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> popyſh deſiples deuided from our maiſters learning, &amp; example the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which hathe ſought nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g in this life &amp; learni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ſaue peace, ſaing my peace I leue w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you, my peace I geue vnto you, the ſonne of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is not come to deſtroye y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoule, but to ſaue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which was loſt O y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> excellent prince turne y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wyſdome of God, whiche ſayeth. O turne you vnto my creacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, lo I wil expreſſe my mynd vnto you, &amp; make you vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d my wordes, ſet your affeccyon vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ryghteouſnes ye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be Iudges of the earth. Be wyſe nowe therfore (o ye kinges) be lerned ye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are Iudges of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth, ſet your luſt
<pb facs="tcp:8679:10"/>
vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wyſdom y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye maye reygne for euermore.<note place="margin">Pro. i. Sapi. i. Pſal. ii. Sapi. vi.</note> And remember wherto ye ar called namely to punyſh euyl do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ears, as theues &amp; murtherers, hore-hunters &amp; breakers of wedlocke i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al kindes, wytches, buggers Raue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhers of weme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, mourtherars, extor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyners, ſtretrobers, to depoſe al falſe &amp; blind learners, let them be of what ſecte or name ſoeuer he or they be, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ther Antichryſtes learninge, beaſtly lyuing, blaſphemyng &amp; ſcla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derynge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> almyghty maieſtie of god Chryſt Ieſu, &amp; the holy ghoſt &amp; the euerlaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng ſafemakyng word y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel of Ieſu Chriſt. To theſe thinges are ye called, as it is manifeſtly ler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ſcriptures,<note place="margin">Exo. xviii. and .xxiii.ii. Pa. xiv. Roma. xiii i. Petre. ii</note> as in Exo xviii.xxiii.ii. pa. xix. Ro. xiii.i. pe. ii. ſuche prynces hath bene. Ezecheas Ioſeas, Dauid, Ioſaphat, zoroba, bel &amp; yet mo, whiche alwayes vſed the offyce accordinge to the decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racion of godes worde. They haue
<pb facs="tcp:8679:11"/>
done alwayes theyr hole diligens to rule the lande in the feare of God, &amp; hath roted out all falſe Prophetes, and Preſtes wyth there Alters and Idols. They haue ſoughe the lawe of the Lorde. The ryght offeryng &amp; Cerymones whiche the Lorde had delyuered vnto the chyldren of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſrael by Moyſes.<note place="margin">Deut. vi</note> The feare of God was in theyr hartes. The boke of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe in theyr ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, therafter haue they lyued. Iudged the folke &amp; pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Lorde that hath called them to ſuche an offyce, they haue ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mytted them ſelues with al ther hole hartes, and hath geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Glory vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to the God of there fathers, Abram, Iſac, and Iacob. Lyke as Dauid dyd playeng daunſynge before the lordes Arke, and was gyrded wyth a lynnen Ephode, ſo that he was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preued of hys wyfe Michol. What hathe he anſwered I wyll playe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lorde,<note place="margin">ii. Reg. vi.</note> and wyll yet be more
<pb facs="tcp:8679:11"/>
vyle the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo, and wylbe meke harted meke in myne owne ſyght. O thou excellent Prynce beleue the Goſpell of Ieſu Chryſt, feare the ſtronge punyſhment of God, loue ryghte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes, do ryght to wydowes and fatherles. Iudge right betwene ney<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>boure &amp; neyghboure, feare no mans countenaunce, deſpice no mans ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelnes, punyſhe with deſcretion all euyl doynges, let learned men prech Godes worde in your lande, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> God hathe geuen vnto you, and let them lyue by you, whiche the Lorde hathe called and choſen. So ſhal your ſeate remayne for euermore. The Lorde guyde your hart to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loue of god and to the pacient wyghtyng for Chryſte Amen.<note place="margin">Sapi. vi. Pro. xxix. ii. teſſa. iii.</note>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>By your poore ſeruante Thomas Lancaſter.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:8679:12"/>
            <head>¶To the (right) Congregation of God of whiche your grace is ſupreame heade next immediat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye vnder God.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y dearlye belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu, I lerne wyth Chryſte Ieſus, and that out cho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſen veſſell ſaynt Paull y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all they that are Baptyſed thorowe the holy gooſt, and is become one body that is one congregatyon of God,<note place="margin">Ephe. v.</note> or ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye churche withoute ſpot or wrincle or anye ſuch thynge, buylded vpon the fundacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Apoſtles &amp; Pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phetes, Ieſus Chriſt himſelfe being the hed corner ſtone in whom what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer
<pb facs="tcp:8679:12"/>
buyldynge is coupled togy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it groweth vnto an holy Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in the Lorde in whom ye alſo ar buylded togyther to be an habyta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon of God throwe the holy gooſt,<note place="margin">Ephe. ii.</note> gathered out of Iewes and Grekes men and women fre and bonde. Yea I ſay gathered out of al the chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God, whiche is ſtrowed in all the hole worlde and is become a true bride of Ieſu chryſte.<note place="margin">Gala. iii.</note> Theſe I ſaye that are thus borne from aboue out of God y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father whiche new byrthe muſt be alonly throw y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> frutful ſede that is Goddes worde.</p>
            <p>For our fyrſt byrth whiche is out of our fyrſt father Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is hole blind defe wythout vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dinge in god<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye knowledge,<note place="margin">e. Cor. iiiii Ia. i. i. Pet. i Ro. viii</note> earthelye mynded whoſe ende is deathe.</p>
            <p>Therfore yf we wyll be partakers of the Lordes table, we muſte be borne anewe oute of the frut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb facs="tcp:8679:13"/>
ſede of gods worde they ar co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerted and changed out of infyde<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lite to fidelite out of earthly into hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uenly out of fleſh into ſpirit out of vnryghteouſnes into ryghteouſnes out of euel into good, yea out of the earthly Adam into the heauenly A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam which is Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yſt Ieſus.<note place="margin">Ro. viii</note> Theſe are like faſſhioned vnto the ſhape of Ieſus Chryſt,<note place="margin">i. Io. ii Hebre. iii. Io. i. Phili. ii.</note> whiche is the fyrſt be gotten amonge many brethren and walkes as he hath walked, theſe are the ryght brethren of Ieſus Chryſt borne with him from aboue oute of god the father and is like mindid as he, theſe are the newe Eua, the clean chaſt bryde of Ieſus Chriſt fleſh of his fleſh and bones of hys bones.<note place="margin">Ephe. v. Gala. v. Colo. iii. Ro. vi.</note> Theſe crucifie the fleſhe with luſt &amp; deſier theſe haue rightly buryed ther ſynnes wyth hym in Baptime and ar riſen with him in a new lyfe theſe are vpryghtly Baptiſed throwe the holy goſt with all the true members
<pb facs="tcp:8679:13"/>
of Chriſt in that vndefiled bodye of Ieſu Chryſte that is his congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio,<note place="margin">i. Cor. xii Gala. iii.</note> theſe ar thei y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> haue put one chriſt and prynte him out in ther lyuing. Theſe ſeekes nothynge in all there thoughtes wordes and workes, but the prayſe of god and the ſaluation of ther brethren,<note place="margin">Math. v.</note> they loue them that hates them, they do good for euell, they pray for them that perſecute the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they are troden out of al fleſhly luſt and deſires as couetuouſnes pryde, vncleanlynes whordom backbiting ſclaunderyng, enuye, murther, theft, glottony, falſe holynes, and al Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry. There meditacion is day and nyght in the lawe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyſe in good and ar ſadde in euill. They render not euell for euell, but much more good for euell, they ſeke not there owne profyte, but that is, there neyghbours profect bothe in ſoule and body. They giue meate to the hungry, drinke to the thurſty, clo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thes
<pb facs="tcp:8679:14"/>
the naked, herber the herberles delyuer priſoners, they viſet the ſic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke comforte the comfortles, they in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtruct them that go aſtraye, yea they ſet there liues for there brethren like as our Sauiour Ieſu Chryſte the Prophetes and Apoſtles haue done there thoughtes are chaſt, ther wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des are truth and with ſalt be ſprin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kle, ye that is ye, and nay is nay, al ther workes are donne in the feare of god. To ſuche a congregacyon, is lice<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſed to haue the Communio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſtes body and blood as here after ſhalbe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">i. Cor. xi.</note>The Lord Ieſus the ſame night in whych he was betrayed toke brea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de and whan he had gyuen thankes he brake it and ſaid take ye and eate this is my body which is broken for you,<note place="margin">Mat. xxvi Mar, xiiii Luke. xxiii</note> this do ye in the remembrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of me, after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame maner alſo toke he the cuppe when ſupper was done
<pb facs="tcp:8679:14"/>
ſaying this cuppe is the new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment in my blud, this do ye as often as ye drinke it in remembraunce of me, and they haue dronke al here of. Theſe are the worde w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which chriſt hath inſtituted his holi ſupper, with which wordes, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> learned of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world haue wonderfullye foughte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in few yeres haue ſhede much inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent blood for it, when they counted the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues wyſe, they became fooles, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pryncipalleſt in this they haue not towched,<note place="margin">Ro. i.</note> namely what people y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it belongeth vnto. We haue not one title that commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des vs y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhuld diſpute of it, but that we ſhuld be di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ligent, that we myght be found wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thy, to be partakers of the declaracio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and benefite, that is receaued in it, as S. Paul teacheth let euery man examin himſelfe and ſo let him eate of the breade and drynke of the cuppe. &amp;c.<note place="margin">Cor, xi</note> Wherfore we are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrayned, to ſaye goodnyght to all
<pb facs="tcp:8679:15"/>
hye diſputacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, where throw diuiſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> commeth deſyring the lord alwayes that we myght be found worthy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceauers of it according to the lordes commaundement.</p>
            <p>¶This holy ſupper, hath our ſaui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>our Ieſus chriſt left behind him vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der,<note place="margin">Luk. xxii.</note> bread and wine ſaying take and eate, this is my body whych is geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for you, this do in the remembrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of me. In whiche holye Supper is declared, vnto vs. Fyrſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vnſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able fauoure and loue of our lorde Ieſus Chriſt, which is come in this world, not to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dempne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world, but that the worlde throwe hym myght be ſaued.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Io. iii.</note>O wonderful loue of god he hath ſent no Angel no Patriarke nor pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phet,<note place="margin">Ro. viii.</note> he is come him ſelfe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude of ſynfull fleſhe. Ye he which knew no ſynne made himſelfe to be ſinne for vs, that we by hys meanes ſhuld be that righteouſnes whyche
<pb facs="tcp:8679:15"/>
before god is alowed, not that chriſt is any ſuche ſynne (that be farre) He was that Lambe without ſpot whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che did do ſynne,<note place="margin">ii. Cor. v. Exo. xii. i. pet. ii.</note> neyther was there gile fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de in his mouth,<note place="margin">Eſay. liii.</note> but he was that frewilling offring for ſynne as Eſay as ſayeth he was wonded for our offences and ſmitte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for our wic<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kednes, he is offred, for ſo it hath pleaſed him, therfore is he called ſin that is an offering for ſynne.</p>
            <p>O almyghtiful god, who can kepe in ſecrete, the vnmeaſurable grace &amp; mercy declared vpon vs,<note place="margin">Ro. viii</note> miſerable ſynners but muſt breake out and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſſe the afore the whole worlde, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> mouthe and worke, lyfe and ſoule, Saynt Paul teacheth that god ſpa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red not hys owne ſonne,<note place="margin">Ro. v</note> but gaue him for vs all, yea whylle we were yet ſynners and vngodlye. Chriſte dyed for vs the righteous for the vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>righteouſe, ye y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vndefiled offer lame is brente throwe the glowynge fyer
<pb facs="tcp:8679:16"/>
of loue vpon the Iebett of the croſſe yea the creatoure of all creatures, is broken frome aboue to beneth, yea he that is farer then the chyldren of men hath neyther bewty nor fauour he is diſpiſed and abhored of al men yea he is ſuche a man as full of ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe,<note place="margin">Pſal. lv.</note> and as one that hath good ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peryence of infyrmytes, yea he is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened amonge the tranſgreſſors, the innocent muſt beare the hole falte of Adam, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Prophet ſayeth. I paid them the thynge that I neuer toke. All this hath our ſauyour declared vnto vs not throw our deſeruynge but as Saynte Paule learneth the kyndnes and loue of our ſauyoure god to man warde apered not by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dedes of ryghteouſnes whiche we wrought, but accordyng to his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy he ſaued vs,<note place="margin">Eſay. l, iii.</note> for ther was no gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce,<note place="margin">Pſal. xl.ix</note> nor mercy, nor no remyſſion of ſynnes by the father, vnto the tyme that our ſauiour Ieſu Chryſt hade
<pb facs="tcp:8679:16"/>
taken vpon hym the ſynnes of the worlde.<note place="margin">Titus .iii.</note> For as by one mans dyſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedyence many became ſynners, ſo by the obedyente of one ſhal manye be made ryghteous.</p>
            <p>Nowe for aſmuche as when he was in the ſhape of God,<note place="margin">Roma. v Phelip .ii.</note> made him ſelft of no reputacyon goen out of hym ſelfe, and wher he was immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, is be come mortall takinge vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hym the ſhape of a ſeruaunte, to the intent that he myght ſerue vs al and was founde in hys apperell as a man very fleſhe and bloud and in all thynges lyke vnto his brethren,<note place="margin">Luke .ii. Iohan .i. Hebre. ii. Phelip .ii.</note> ſauynge ſynne, he humbled hym ſelfe and became obedyent vnto his father vnto death, euen the deathe of the Croſſe, throwe whiche death it pleaſed the father, that in hym ſhulde all fulnes dwell and by hym to reconcile all thinges to him ſelfe and to ſet at peace by him throw the bloude of his Croſſe, both thinges
<pb facs="tcp:8679:17"/>
in heauen and thynges in earth and is become an offerynge and ſacry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyce of ſwete ſauour to god his dear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly beloued father.<note place="margin">Colo i.</note> This is fruteful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly declared vnto vs in this holy Supper namely throw that breade that fleſhe that he hathe geuen for vs,<note place="margin">Ephe. vi. Mar. xiiii</note> and throwe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Cuppe that bloud whiche he ſhede for manye, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſſyon of ſynnes, and ſhall be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs a remembraunce tyll he come. Nowe bycauſe that it is a come<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vſe that a token of remembraunce hath the name of the thing that is reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred by it.<note place="margin">Luke .xxii.</note> Therfore hathe Chryſte called the breade hys bodye, and the wyne his bloude, not that he is in ſubſtance in breade and wyne,<note place="margin">i. Cor. ii. Exod. xii.</note> but that we ſhulde remember hym there by. Lykewyſe as the Eaſter Lambe was called the paſſynge by, and yet was it not in it ſelfe the very paſſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g by, but a token of remembraunce of the paſſinge by. Seynge nowe that
<pb facs="tcp:8679:17"/>
the Earſter lambe hath the name of the thyng that the Iſraelites remem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bred by it, and wherby they myght euerlaſtingly kepe in remembraun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce the benefytes of god therfore it is conuenyent that Chryſt called the breade hys bodye and the vyne hys bloude, becauſe that we ſhulde re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member therby his death and paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> yea the onely ſacrifyce of his bodye whiche he hathe ſuffered to be bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and his bloude to be ſhede for vs, not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat the materyall bodye of Chryſt is in the bread nor his bloud in the vyne. Yet neuertheles is the ſupper of our Lorde a partakynge ſpiritually of the bodye and bloude of Chryſte,<note place="margin">i. Colo x.</note> as Sainte Paule ſaieth is not the cuppe of thankes gyuing wherwyth we gyue thankes a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takinge of the bloud of Chryſt; and the breade that we breake; is it not the partaking of the bodye of chriſt and to the intente that this may the
<pb facs="tcp:8679:18"/>
more playnely appere vnto your vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derſtandinge, ye ſhall ſe the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryſon betwex the Paſchall Lambe and our ſacramente.</p>
            <p>The Paſcall Lambe was inſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted and eaten the nyght before the chyldren of Iſraell were delyuered frome Egypte. Lykewyſe was the ſacramente inſtituted and eaten the nyght before we were delyuered fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> oure ſynnes. The Paſcall Lambe was a very lambe in dede, and ſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacramente is very bread in dede.</p>
            <p>The Paſcal Lambe was called the paſſynge by of the Lorde, which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed the power of Pharao, and delyuered them. The Sacramente is called the bodye of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord which deſtroyed the power of the deuell &amp; delyuered vs. The chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell were but ones delyuered frome Egypte notwythſtandyng they dyd eate euery yere y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lambe to kepe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dede in perpetual remembrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo Chryſt bought &amp; redemed vs but
<pb facs="tcp:8679:18"/>
once for al, although y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacramente therof be dayly broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> among vs to kepe the benefyt in continuall me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morye. As many as dyd eate y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call lambe in fayth &amp; beleued god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des worde as touchyng ther delyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce frome Egypte ware as ſure thorowe fayth as they were ſure of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lambe by eatyng it. So as many as do eate this ſacrament in fayth &amp; beleue godes worde as touchinge ther delyueraunce frome ſinne are as ſure of ther delyueraunce throw fayth as they are ſure of the breade by eati<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g it. Nowe ſe ye what y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> paſcal lambe was to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iſraelytes, &amp; what y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacrament is vnto vs. So y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaint Paule witneſſeth clerly, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful eate the body of Chryſt ſpyritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allye vnder the breade and wine, As a bryde receaueth her houſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d with a ryng euen ſo receaueth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faythful chryſt to be his owne &amp; euerlaſtyng ſaluacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; where as diuers writers
<pb facs="tcp:8679:19"/>
wyl haue that the bodylye preſence ſhuld be in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> breade is a great miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>underſtandyng of Gods word, yea it is agreable to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Papiſtes or Anti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chriſtes doctrine, whych is contrary both to our fayth and al hole ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Ro. viii.</note>For we beleue and holye Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture beareth witnes, that Chryſte, after his reſurrection is aſcendid vp into heauen,<note place="margin">Ma. xxviii</note> and ſitteth vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> right hand of his almyghty father, and a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bydeth there as concernyng his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyly preſence. But ſperitually hath he promyſed to abide with vs in his worde to the ende of the worlde.</p>
            <p>Mathe. xxviii.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Hebru. x</note>And ſeyng now that our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſt as concernynge hys bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dylye preſence abydeth at the right hand of his father, ſo can nor maye not the bodye of Chryſte be in the breade, and agayne it is agaynſt al truth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Chriſt at one time hath bene
<pb facs="tcp:8679:19"/>
in manye or dyuyrſe places as tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chynge his bodye. Furthermore we dayly ſee what dredful Idolatry is ſpronge out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> carnall vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dynge of thys words of chriſt. This is my body &amp; yet dayly ſpringeth to the great abomynable ſclaunder of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> honour of god, ſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> men worſhyp a pece of brede, for ther god whych is growen in the ground, broken in the myl, and baked in an yrong, yea and hold that to be there maker. And ye do yet as the Papiſtes locke hym in gold and ſyluer, not remembrynge what Paul &amp; Stephen wytneſſeth ſayng.<note place="margin">Acts. vii and .xvii</note> The moſt hieſt wyl not dwel in Temples y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are made wyth mens hande take hede we haue mocked long ynough wyth God and his ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly worde,</p>
            <p>Secondarly we are exhorted in this holy ſupper to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vnitye loue &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> congregacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of god, becauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we (though we be many)
<pb facs="tcp:8679:20"/>
yet are one bread and one body,<note place="margin">i. Cor. x.</note> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is one body in Chriſt Ieſu like as S. Paul ſayeth we many are one body and one breade in as much as we al are partakers of one bread. For like as the members of one body are not in ſtryfe one agaynſt another but in charitable vnite ſarueth one another So may ther be no ſtrife nor debate in the congregacion of God.<note place="margin">i. Cor. xii</note> They muſt al ſpeake one thyng ther muſt be no diſſenſion among the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hauyng one hart, one ſoule, one mynd, &amp; one meanyng.<note place="margin">i. Cor. i</note> There may be no ſtrife in the fayth, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in mekenes of mind euery man eſteme other better than himſelfe to the prayſe of God and to the alouyng and faythful ſeruice of all the chyldren of god.<note place="margin">Phelip .ii.</note> For likewiſe as the outward members of one bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye wyl gladly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte helpe &amp; ſerue another, ſo doth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> congregacyon of god, yf one ſuffer, al ſuffers w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> him If one be had in honour al is glad.<note place="margin">i Cor. xii.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:8679:20"/>
Alſo euery man ſhall ſerue his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther both bodyly and goſtli likewiſe as our ſauiour Ieſus Chriſte hathe ſerued vs both w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his life and death not onely to deal w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> them, gold,<note place="margin">Math. xx. Luke. xxii.</note> ſyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer &amp; land and houſe Kowe, calfe or any ſuch thing,<note place="margin">Ephe. iiii.</note> but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bludy laboure y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we get w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our owne ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des ſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhuld only care &amp; take thought for him ſelfe and not care nor looke vpon his brothers lake, but the one muſt helpe the other in al things ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie where he can or may,<note place="margin">Gala. vi.</note> and no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſt ſeke that, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is his, but eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one the others welth.</p>
            <p>And likewiſe as of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> graynes of corne, can not be baken breade,<note place="margin">Philip .ii.</note> but throw fyer, euen ſo can not the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregacion be a ryght ſpirituall lyfe (wherof paul ſpeaketh) but through bunrnynge loue and charytye and ſo the Chryſtyan congregatyon to be one lofe for lykewyſe as many graynes are Sowen,<note place="margin">i. Cor. x</note> to the intent
<pb facs="tcp:8679:21"/>
that breade ſhuld be baken of them ſo ſoweth the great father of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſholde hys precious wheate into the aker or ground of this world to the inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that they ſhuld become one lofe and alſo vſe the ſupper of the Lorde ryghtlye after the wordes of Paule we many are one breade and one bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dye in as moch as we are partakers of one breade,<note place="margin">i. Cor. x.</note> for as the body is one and hath many members, and all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> members of the body though they be many yet are but one bodye euen ſo is chryſt. Ye at the body of chriſt and members one of another. Ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore let euery man loke wel to his vo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cation.<note place="margin">Sa. xii i. Cor. xli. Ephe. iiii.</note> For god hath ordeyned in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> congregacion ſome Prophets, ſome Apoſtles and ſome to beleeuers and hirdes. Let no man boſt himſelfe of hys byrth, lernyng &amp; Ryches, for as we are manye members in one body and al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers haue not one office. So we beyng manye, are one body
<pb facs="tcp:8679:21"/>
in Chryſte and euery man amonge our ſelues one anothers members. Seinge that we haue dyuerſe gyf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes accordynge to the grace that is gyuen vnto vs. If anye man haue the gyfte of Propheſye, let hym ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue it that it be agreynge to the faith Let hym that hath an offyce wayte on hys offyce,<note place="margin">Ro. xij</note> let hym that teacheth take hede to hys doctryne. Let hym that exhorteth gyue attendaunce to hys exhortacyon.<note place="margin">i. Pet. iiii.</note> If any man gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue let hym do it with ſynglenes let hym that rewleth do it with dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. If anye man ſhewe mercye let hym do it wyth cherfulnes, and let loue be amonge you wythoute dyſſimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation,<note place="margin">i. Cor. vii.</note> and euerye man abyde in the ſame ſtate wherin he is called, no nother wyſe than to the edifyenge of the bodye of Chryſte, whyche is hys congregation.<note place="margin">Ephe. iiii</note> And thus is this holy Supper of oure Lorde. Fyrſte
<pb facs="tcp:8679:22"/>
a remembraunce of the death of our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſte whiche he ſuffred for vs,<note place="margin">i. Petre. ii</note> throw which deathe we ar al reconciled. Secondarlye it is an inſtruction of the pure cleane &amp; vndefyled loue, whych is amonge the congregation of god lyke as I haue declared afore as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> breade is made of manye Cornes, and is one bread and as the Wyne is made of manye Grapes, and yet is one wine ſo are we many me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers and but one bodye, whiche is chriſt.</p>
            <p>My dearly beloued in Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu, let euery man ſe earneſtly to, and proue himſelfe accordynge to ſaynt Paules learnynge, that he come not to the table of the Lorde, bicauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it hathe bene ſo accuſtomed eyther throwe fayned holynes or deſyre of worldly honour or diſceat, but oute of a pure cleane and vndefyled hart and ſo eate of the bread and drinke of the cuppe for he that eateth or
<pb facs="tcp:8679:22"/>
drynkethe it vnworthylye eateth &amp; drynketh his owne damnacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For al they that wyl come &amp; ſit at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lords Table,<note place="margin">Mat. v.vi</note> they muſt be founde fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful mercyful, louynge, kynde, pyty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and obedyente, wythout diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion wythout hatred, wythout pride wythout couetouſnes, that wicked eye muſte be plucked out, that fleſh muſte be mortyfyed, that euell hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge eare ſtopped, that clattering tounge tamed, that fleſhelye harte cyrcumſiced youre blouddy handes clenſed, your belyes meaſured, and your fete compelled wyth the Lords word, ye muſt haue afrewilling ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayll agaynſte the Deuel,<note place="margin">Vide qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les erunt qui menſe erunt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipes.</note> the world and the fleſhe, that ye may be able to reſyſte in the euyll daye, and ſtande perfecte in all thinges, that is in the wyll of God, youre loynes muſte be girded wyth truthe hauynge on the breaſte plate of ryghteouſnes &amp; hauynge ſhoes on your feit, that
<pb facs="tcp:8679:23"/>
ye maye be prepared for the Goſpell of peace. He muſt be well veaponed wyth the ſhylde of fayth wherwith he maye quence all the fyery dartes of Sathan,<note place="margin">Ephe. vi.</note> he muſt haue on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met of ſaluacyon, and be gyrded with the ſwerd of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſprete, which is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worde of god, he muſt be a me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber ſerueable and prophetable accordi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to his power, he muſt be mynded lyke vnto oure ſauyoure Ieſus Chryſt, as he was what time he kepe this holye ſupper or communyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his derely beloued brethren. He toke breade and wyne and gaue thankes gaue it to his diſciples &amp; ſayde, this is my bodye and my bloude whiche is broken for youe herewyth decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge his godly loue,<note place="margin">vide bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficia chriſti erga nos.</note> fauoure and mercy vpon his derely beloued bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, euen as though he would ſay my derely beloued chyldren, ſo farre hath youre loue led me, and your fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uoure drawen me, that I haue for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken
<pb facs="tcp:8679:23"/>
the dominyon of my heauenly father and hathe taken vpon me to be come youre ſeruaunte to ſerue you in all thynges,<note place="margin">Ezech. xxx.iiii.</note> 
               <note place="margin">Hebre. ii.</note> bycauſe I ſaye that ye were all as ſcattered ſhepe goynge aſtraye,<note place="margin">Pſa. xxiii.</note> and that there was no man that ſought youe, but that ye were all meate to the grypinge, &amp; and ryuenge wolues, and that there was no man to delyuer youe.<note place="margin">Ezech, xvi</note> But that ye were wonded vnto death &amp; that there was no man to playſter you.<note place="margin">Luke. x.</note> Therfore am I come out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> boſome of my father &amp; become lyke vnto my brether a ſtraunger a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunt, a worme and no man, a very ſcorne of men and the outcaſt of peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple, wandrynge in this wylde wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dernes of this world I haue ſought you in cytes &amp; countres, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynes &amp; vayelles, myſerable haue I founde you. Dume, Deafe blind Cryple, Pore and naked, my ſeruice haue I declared vpon you, youre
<pb facs="tcp:8679:24"/>
ſynnes, haue I repreued your febel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, I haue borne, yea I haue ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed you vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my ſhulders into my fathers houſe,<note place="margin">Luke. x. Re. xvii. Eze. xxiiii Ioh. vvi.</note> I haue deliuered you out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mouthes of hellyſhe lyons, and beares your foull ſtynkynge wondes, I haue ſo ſoftly healed the peace of my father, haue I declared vnto you, your nakednes haue I clothed, and youre pouertye I haue healped. I haue gyue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto you fete hartes, eyes, eares, and mouthes, to walke to vnderſtande, to knowe, to heare, and to ſpeake the wordes of euerlaſtynge lyfe. I haue brought you into the knowledge of al rygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes, I haue learned you the wyll of my heauenly father. And to the intente that ye maye know that I am the true meſſenger of my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſo haue I declared it vnto you by my great wonders and myraeles Se nowe my derely beloued childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nowe is my houre come, the longe-time is ful ended, now y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I can ſerue
<pb facs="tcp:8679:24"/>
ſerue you no longer, wyth my lyfe &amp; learninge, nowe wyll I laſte of all ſerue you with my fleſhe and bloud and bytter death, For this cauſe am I come amonge you, and leaue you this breade and this cuppe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer ye ſhal come togither, ye ſhal vſe it in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> remembrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of me, &amp; ſay dearly beloued brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in chriſt Ieſu we y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are here congregated together in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lordes name,<note place="margin">Quo ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo celebre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tur coena dominica.</note> this bread &amp; this cuppe hath our ſauiour Ieſu chriſt lefte behind him, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhuld remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber him therby. O how fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dely hath our ſauiour Ieſu chryſte ſerued vs both w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his lyfe &amp; death, &amp; declaring here in eating this bread &amp; drinking this cuppe,<note place="margin">Tales eri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus erga a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lios qualis chriſtus er<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ga nos.</note> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhulde folowe his bliſſed example ſeruyng one another lyke as one me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber another w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> learning w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> inſtructo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pelling, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> reproufe, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> mercy, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> loue &amp; all nedefull neceſſares as we haue fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our ſauiour Ieſu chriſt towerd vs. Now as we are thus co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregated
<pb facs="tcp:8679:25"/>
in ſuch a Chriſten fayth vnyte &amp; obedient,<note place="margin">i. Cor. xi</note> ſo haue we godes worde, and promyſe a ſpirytuall ioye myrth &amp; coumfort of the houſe of Iſraell,<note place="margin">Mat. xxvi</note> ſo reioſes the congregaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of God in that beutyfull bryde knowenge well that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> broken bread is a pertakynge of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bodye of chriſt and the cuppe of blyſſing, a parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge of the bloude of Chryſt whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is ſhede for manye for the remy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon of ſynnes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſia et communio Chriſtiano cum</note>O what gloryous banket is this where in the hungrye ſoule, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde man recayueth that inuyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble breade &amp; heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly foode which is chriſt Ieſus. O glorious co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>grega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wherin ar no ſha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ful ſonges nor vnprofytable wordes, ſaue al onely brotherlye inſtruction and geuynge thankes to our ſauyour Ieſu chriſt O gloryous congregacion wher no wanton eyes is caſting here &amp; there but all bente to the helpe and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort
<pb facs="tcp:8679:25"/>
of thy pore brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. O glorious congregacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wherin men vſe not to drynke, dans, nor play, but wher me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are dronke in the wyſdome of god, there ſhall the ſoule be ioeful in the holy ghoſte playeng, and daunſing afore the Lorde. My derely beloued in Chryſt Ieſu, ye that are ſo dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bought with the precyous bloud of our ſauyour Ieſus chryſt, wake vp leaue of it is more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tyme, fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re the lordes worde, and fle from the deuilles table, for this is no ſupper of the Lorde, whiche the blinde vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned Papyſtes haue learned and vſed to this tyme, no I ſaye it is no ſupper of our lorde,<note place="margin">
                  <p>Maximu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diſcrimen intercenam dominica<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> et cenam Antechriſti anam.</p>
                  <p>Cena mu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di.</p>
               </note> whiche is mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred and ſoulde of an Antychryſtes teacher a Sodomitical begger a ba<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bylonyſh marchande, the whiche yf he do not repente and amend, is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſtyngly curſed and banyſſhed from the preſtes of god.</p>
            <p>The Supper of our Lorde muſt
<pb facs="tcp:8679:26"/>
be miniſtred of hym that is called of a Chryſtian congregacion compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led throw the holy ghoſt to come in to the Lordes vyneyarde, or heuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly harueſt which is founde without faute, accordynge to the declaracion of godes worde, both in his lyfe and learning.<note place="margin">i. Cor v. and .vi.</note> It is no ſupper, that is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued of dronkerdes, fornycatours worſhyppers of Images,<note place="margin">Gala. v.</note> aduoute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, weakelyng abuſers of them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues with the mankind theues coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous, curſed ſpeakers, murtherers, traytours, and ſhedders of innocent bloude. But it is a ſupper to them y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> walkes afore God, and the worlde in loue, ioye, peace, long ſufferynge, gentylnes, goodnes, faythfulnes, meakenes, and temporaunce, which deſyers to ſpende there fleſhe and bloude, for the glory of God. It is no ſupper where men haue no other thinge but ſhryueng, faſting knoc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, knelyng, becking bouing, weſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyng
<pb facs="tcp:8679:26"/>
ſetting out of the bodye,<note place="margin">In cena do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mini non externus ſed i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ternus requiritus ornatus.</note> with fayre clothes, holding vp of handes and knocking vpon the breaſt, but to them that is founde with a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, thankefull hearte and a cleane conſcience and vnfayned loue. All they that haue not this faith, &amp; loue and is not bound hollie w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the bond of loue, to his neyboure, ſeruing him in his nede, with al diligence &amp; wyl, and likewiſe ſet downe at the table of the Lorde. I feare me that he ſhal receaue with that Hipocrite Iudas not lyfe, but euerlaſting death, and eateth and drynketh the communio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Balial and not of Chriſt, though he ſpeake with the tonges of men, &amp; Angels and though he coulde pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſy and vnderſtand al ſecretes, &amp; and all knowledge,<note place="margin">Videat ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi quiſque qui accedit ad cenam domni.</note> &amp; yf he had faith y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he coulde moue mountaynes, and though he beſtowed al his goods to fede y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pore, and though he gaue his
<pb facs="tcp:8679:27"/>
body to be burned, and yet had no loue, it profyteth nothinge, ſo that he doth not loue out of the verye grounde of his harte, wyth worke &amp; truth whiche loue is the verye band of perfectnes,<note place="margin">Cor. xiii. ii. Io. iii.</note> and the chefe of all thynges.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Colo. ii.</note>Therefore I exorte euery man that wyll be partakers of the lordes ſupper,<note place="margin">i. Cor. xi.</note> that he ryghtly proue hym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe accordyng to Paules learning For all they y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truſt vnto ther owne ryghteouſnes,<note place="margin">Qui confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit in ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quo quam in chriſto maleidit.</note> or vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the learnings and commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of men, and not vpon ryghteouſnes and deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge, and bloude of our ſauyour Ieſu Chryſte, bleſſed myght he be, and goeth lykewyſe to the table of the lord the eateth his owne damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon.<note place="margin">Qui ada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mat te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>po ralia plus quam Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtiana in digne man ducat.</note> Lykewyſe all they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyſed and haue gyue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> themſelfe wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly vnder the falſe prophetes in heryſe &amp; vngodlines, and wyll not be reformed, &amp; lykewiſe go to the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb facs="tcp:8679:27"/>
of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord, they eate theyr owne damnacion. Lykewyſe all they that loue better tranſitori thynges than the glory of God, &amp; hys holy worde as golde, ſyluer, wyfe, children, lyfe and lyuing, and goeth to the table of the lord, he eateth his owne dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacyon. Lykewyſe all they that wyl not gyue them ſelues frewyllyng to the ſeruyce of theyr neyghbours w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al that they haue receaued at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hand of god, viſeble and vnuyſeble,<note place="margin">Qui ſibi tantum mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>do viuit et non aliis, iudicium ſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bi mandu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat.</note> and goeth to the table of the Lorde, they eate theyr owne damnacyon. Lyke wyſe he that boſteth himſelfe ogai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt his chryſten brother of his Byrth, ryches, wyſdome bewty,<note place="margin">Qui glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atur in va<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nis et ſi ep fu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> non cog<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>noſcito ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le edit.</note> or any ſuch thinge and wyl not know that he is a ſtinkyng Caryon, and foule fleſh euel &amp; folyſhe before the eyes of the lorde, and goeth to the table of the lorde, he eateth his damnacyon, lyke wyſe al they that boaſte them ſelues of the name of Chryſt and notwyth<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtandinge
<pb facs="tcp:8679:28"/>
lyues accordinge to the fleſhe, as pryde, couetouſnes, aduo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trye fornication vncleanes wanto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, Idolatrye witchecrafte hatred variaunce, zele, wrath, ſtryfe, ſedicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſectes, iniurye, murther dronkenes, gluttony and ſuche lyke, and doth dayly with there curſed &amp; vngodly lyfe,<note place="margin">Gala. v. Ephe. v. i. Cor. v. Ro. viii</note> cruſifye the ſonne of God, and and go lykewyſe to the table of the lorde, he eateth his damnation. For all they that commyte ſuche thinges ſhall not meryte the kingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of god.<note place="margin">Apo. xxi</note> 
               <note place="margin">Aperte ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>li. pellendi ſunt a cen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ra.</note> And therfore are they vnworthye to come to the Supper of the Lorde, becauſe they haue no communio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the body and bloude of our ſauiour Ieſu chriſt. No noman may be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to come to the holy ſupper of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord, let him be of what ſtate or degre ſoeuer they be ſo farre forth as hys iniquite and ſinne is manifeſt and knowen to the congregacion,<note place="margin">i. Cor. x.</note> which is a communion or congregacion of the body and bloude of chryſt. But
<pb facs="tcp:8679:28"/>
he muſt be excomunicated and cutte of with goddes worde, vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme that he do penaunce &amp; decleare him ſelfe to be obedient to the goſpell of our ſauiour Ieſu Chriſt whiche ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comunicacion is manyfeſt in theſe Chapters folowinge as in Mat, vii xvi.x.xvi. i. Cor. v.vi.. Phi. iii.ii. Teſſa. iii. i. Timoth. vi.ii. Timoth. iii. titus. iii.ii. Iahn. i. which excom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>municacion, yf I lyue by the helpe of God I wyll ſet out at large. But as for them that are inwardly well and couereth themſelfe outwardly w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſhininge mantell of holines like as Iudas did w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſuche ſhall the congregaco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue nothing to do,<note place="margin">hipocritas iudicabit</note> but let y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lorde iudge the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which is a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer &amp; knower of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all hartes, for by him nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g is hid nor forgotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iudg y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> knowes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hartes &amp; mindes &amp; ſhal iudge,<note place="margin">Rom. viii. i. Cor. v. Math. xiii Eſay. lxvi.</note> not onli y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> euel workes but alſo Idel wordes, yea y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> though and mocion of the harte. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let euery man examine him ſelfe
<pb facs="tcp:8679:29"/>
fleſh wel and ſo let hym eate of the bread. and drinke of the cuppe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">i. Cor. xi.</note>For he that eateth, and drynketh vnworthylye eateth and drynketh his owne damnatyon.<note place="margin">Luke .xxii.</note> Thus hathe our ſauiour Ieſus Chryſt inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and ordeyned hys holye ſupper both in breade and wyne to be a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of his death and paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as I haue declared afore.<note place="margin">i. Cor. xi. Ephe. v.</note> Throwe whyche death and paſſyon, he hath declared his greate loue towardes vs, and ſecondlye to a renewinge of loue and cleane holding the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of god.<note place="margin">i. Cor. x.</note> And this is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> only inſtitucion and vſe of the ſupper of our Lorde Ieſus chriſt how he and his Apoſtles haue vſed it.</p>
            <p>O mercyfull God haue theſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly ſhameles ſhauelinges altred and chaunged this holy and bleſſed Supper of our lord into abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble blaſphemus Idolatrye, as I ſhall declare here after vnto you.
<pb facs="tcp:8679:29"/>
It is ſo greuous that I ſhal declare vnto you whyche ſhalbe nothynge, but the trueth, that euery Chryſtian hatte maye tremble and quake at it. Therfore ſeke wyth all dyligence y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth to the intent that ye maye kno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>we how pytyfull that we and all the worlde haue ſynned, agaynſte oure Lorde God in this matter.<note place="margin">Antechriſti oblatio.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Fyrſte they haue conuerted and chaunued, thys holye and Bleſſed ſupper, of our Lord wyth ther falſe learnynge and auctoritye out of his ryght vſe and haue lerned it to be a dayly ſacrifice for our ſinnes. This is abominable blaſphemy and piti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full blyndnes that men can not ima<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gyn ſuch another.<note place="margin">Nota ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentes ab<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hominatio<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes.</note> Wyth thys ſame learnyng haue they driuen Chryſte Ieſus out of his fathers ſtoole, out of heauen, and haue ſet in his place an vngodlye preiſt wyth a peace of breade, wyth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame learnyng haue they robed chryſt Ieſus of his euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtyng
<pb facs="tcp:8679:30"/>
and perpetual offyce that is the office of an aduocate, and haue put it vpon a pece of breade and a deuylles ſeruaunt whiche knowes not one title ryght of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word of god Wyth the ſame learning haue they made of no value al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fygures and ſhyne of Moyſes, al the prophicies of the prophittes, al the promyſes of Angelles &amp; al the hole new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment whych alonly ſpeaketh of that only ſacrifyce for ſin,<note place="margin">Cur panis ille immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lationis (vt voca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t) trangatur in tres par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes.</note> which is chriſt Ieſus with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame learnynge haue they take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them al power in hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen earth &amp; hel. Therfore is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> brede of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Idolles table broken in thre pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the fyrſt pece pacifie the god wyth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de they pray for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thirde they delyuer the ſoul y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they offer it for, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this ſame learni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ar they riſen aloft in gold ſyluer in pompe lordlines &amp; honour by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hole world herewith ar they climed vp a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>boue al princes, &amp; haue gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto
<pb facs="tcp:8679:30"/>
the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues gold, ſyluer, churches cloy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſters land, ſand, &amp; the highes places name &amp; power in al la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhuld giue rume to their holynes, feare there name &amp;, highlye prayſe ther gloriouſe office deſiring alwayes, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> throwe this good worke whych is this dayly offringe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they myght be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forted in there ſoule.</p>
            <p>Throw this meanes is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Anthichryſt gotten into his ſeat ſo hie y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Empriours maieſtie,<note place="margin">Medium in quo ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatus eſt Antechriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus.</note> the hieſt pote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> earth who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> god him ſelf co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded to obey muſt knele downe &amp; kyſſe his ſtynkyng fote, ye this is more fredericus Barboroſſa y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t emperour, bicauſe he wold haue letted his knaueri culd get no miſericordia vntill the tyme that A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der Tertius y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prynce of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Babi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lonical coniures had troden vpon this excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Emperour in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> churche dore at Venega, thus hath that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uillyſh offri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g brought in bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dage y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:8679:31"/>
hole worlde. But the Lorde be bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, whiche hath delyuered vs from this fayned ſacryfyce, and golden Calfe,<note place="margin">Eſay. l.iii.</note> and hath declared vnto vs y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> onely hye preſt ouer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houſe of god, whiche remaneth a preſt for euer af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the order of Melchiſideche, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che in the dayes of his fleſhe dyd of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer vp prayers and ſupplycacions wyth ſtrong cryeng and teares vnto hym,<note place="margin">Hebre. v.</note> that was able to ſaue hym fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deathe, and was harde bycauſe of his godlynes, he hath offered one offerynge &amp; a ſacryfyce of ſwete ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure to God,<note place="margin">Ephe. v.</note> he hath ſaieth Saint Paule offered one ſacryfyce for ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, ſat hym done for euer on the ryght hande of God,<note place="margin">Hee. x.</note> and from hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce forth taryeth tyl his foes be made hys footſtole, for wyth one offering hath he made perfect for euer them that are ſanctifyed. This is the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſacryfice wyth which the fathers wrayth is pacyfied, the generacyon
<pb facs="tcp:8679:31"/>
of Adam delyuered heauen, opened and hell ſhut.<note place="margin">Ro. iii. Chriſtus vnica pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peccatis victima</note> For it pleaſed the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that in him ſhuld alfulnes dwel and by hym to reconcile al thynges to hym ſelfe and to ſet at peace by hym throw the blood of hys croſſe, both thynges in heauen and thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges in earth.<note place="margin">i. Colo i.</note> ¶ Now come forth al power and myght and al ye that ar papiſtes with al ye that reken your ſelfe to be learned, that is in Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d and is of the papiſtes opinion thys worde can neyther Angell nor De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell breke,<note place="margin">Hebru. x.</note> namely that with one of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fring he hath made perfecte for euer them that are ſantcyfyed.</p>
            <p>My dearly beloued in Chryſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu, loue your ſoule and loke earneſt lye vpon the lordes wordes. Know ones vnder what learnynge ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes and congregacion ye are? what ſhepards fede you, what brede y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye breake, in what bodiye ar bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d</p>
            <p>O ye chyldren howe longe wyll<note place="margin">Prouer. i.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:8679:32"/>
you loue chyldyſhnes? howe longe wyl ye ſcorners delyte in ſcornynge and the vnwyſe be ennemyes vnto knowledge?<note place="margin">ii. Cor. vi. Apo. xviii. Luke. ix.</note> How longe wil you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne in your ſynnes? howe longe wil ye be bounde wyth the chayn of Infidelite in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> botomles pyt.<note place="margin">Mat. xi.</note> Come out from amonge the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> auoid al falſe learnynge exchew all falſe holynes and let the deade bury the dede, and folow ye after our mayſter Chriſt, enter into hys houſe and take vp vpon you his eaſye yocke and light burthen &amp; ye ſhal fynde reſt in your ſoules as then maye ye boſt youre ſelues of the grace of God the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyuenes of ſynnes, the deſeruing of our Sauiour Ieſus chriſt, &amp; euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtyng lyfe god giue you his grace Amen.</p>
            <p>Secoundarly, they haue taught y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the bread is veri fleſh, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wine very blood &amp; that haue they gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wordes of chriſt literali
<pb facs="tcp:8679:32"/>
ſpoken wherin he ſayeth take &amp; eate this is my bodye .&amp;c. not markynge what Chryſt ſayth in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .vi.<note place="margin">Ioh. vi.</note> of Iohn That is to ſaye it is the ſpirite that quickeneth, the fleſhe profyteth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wordes which I ſpake vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you ar ſpirit &amp; lif, for in this place he meaneth of his owne fleſhe &amp; one ſpirit and he deuideth the ſpirite fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the fleſh, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they myght know throw fayth not onlye the vyſyble parte, but alſo the inuiſible part that was in him and that the wordes whyche he ſpake ware not carnal, but ſpiry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual, for what body ſhuld haue ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſed to be the meat of al the worlde and eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therfore did he make men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of the aſſenſion of the ſonne of man into heauen, that he myght w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> drawe them from the bodyly ymagi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they myght here after learne y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the fleſh was called heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly meat which cometh fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aboue &amp; ſpiritual meat which he wold giue,<note place="margin">Io. vi</note> for chriſte
<pb facs="tcp:8679:33"/>
the wordes that I haue ſpoke vnto you are ſpirite &amp; lyfe,<note place="margin">Iohn. vi.</note> Here you may ſe that Chryſt ſpake it of hys owne fleſhe, and ment playnly that it did nothyng profect as the Papiſtes or infydelles do vnderſtand hym.</p>
            <p>Now all they that wyl not haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glory of ther redemption chaunged into a pece of bread, but deſyreth to haue the ryght miniſtracion of the Chryſtiane tabell they muſt be cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted and condempned as ſwarmers, heritykes and Sacramentates and not only that but muſt be Burned, Drawen,<note place="margin">Miſcrri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus error.</note> Drounned &amp; Hanged. O my dearly beloued in Chryſte Ieſu is not this amiſerable and abonina<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble heriſie, to learne and to make the poore people beleue,<note place="margin">i. Cor. xi.</note> that the euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtynge ſone of God is chaunged or tranſubſtanciated into a peace of breade and ſuppe of wyne, whiche hath gyuen hys body to be broken and hys bloud to be ſhede for vs in
<pb facs="tcp:8679:33"/>
the remiſſion of ſynnes. O beaſtly,<note place="margin">Math. xv.</note> heritikes. The ſcripture ſayeth that, that whiche entreth by the mouthe doth not defile a man, for as Chriſte ſayeth it is caſt forth into the draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght and by the ſame reaſon it folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth, that it dothe not ſanctyfye or make a man holye. But the Sacre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment entreth in by the mouth, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it doth folowe that of it ſelfe, it doth not ſantifie or make holy anye man. And of this text ſhuld folow two inconueniences yf the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t were the naturall bodye of Chryſt, fyrſt it ſhuld folow that the body of Chryſt ſhuld not ſantifye the fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful bicauſe it entreth in by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mouth and agayne it ſhuld folowe that the body of Chryſt ſhuld be caſt out in to the draught which is abominable Wherfore it muſt nedes folow that the Sacrament can not be hys na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural bodye.</p>
            <p>Therfore beleue Gods word it is<note place="margin">Iohn. vi.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:8679:34"/>
the ſpirit that quicknethe, the fleſhe profiteth nothing meanyng to eate it with his tethe, the wordes that I ſpeake vnto you are ſpirit and lyfe, and if it be ſo that ye do not beleue this,<note place="margin">Filius dei non editur carnaliter nec digeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</note> yet beleue that the euerlaſtyng ſoone of god which is with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father can not be eaten with mens teth nor conſumed in no bellye, muche les be deuored with fire, wormes, myſe, rat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes and Apes, which is openly kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in this viſible bread vſed in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny places, But where the congrega<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion of god is gathered together in his name, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> true fayth true loue &amp; obedience and with right miniſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion according to the declaracion of gods worde, there is delyuered vnto the outward man breade and wyne but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inuiſible ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> receaueth throw y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> promyſe of chriſt, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> inuiſible bread and Drinke which is the fleſh and <note place="margin">Similt ꝓ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimili paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citur.</note>blood of our ſauiour Ieſus chryſte which men can neither eate bitte nor
<pb facs="tcp:8679:34"/>
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſume for like wil with like be fede the viſible man is fede wyth vyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble meate namelye bread and wyne &amp; the inuiſible ſpirit, is fede with in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uiſible meate which is chryſt Ieſus Therfore remaneth bread bread, &amp; wyne wyne, for if it ware otherwyſe ſo ware that ſpirituall man fede w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> palpable and viſible breade &amp; wine, &amp; ſo ware that viſible creature nam<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly breade and wyne chaunged in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpiritual and inuiſible ſoone of god the which is not nor can not be as it is manifeſt afore our eyes and ſhal remayne euerlaſtinge.</p>
            <p>O Lorde haue mercye vpon vs for we are more foliſh and haue leſe vnderſtandyng tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the gentles haue had from the begynnynge. For they haue worſhipped for god the ſonne, Mone, and Sterres, whiche do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare power and myght in all wax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge creatures. They haue I ſaye honored open Serpentes and
<pb facs="tcp:8679:35"/>
Dragons with other creatures whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che had power myght and a lyuing ſprite in them, but we whiche boſte oure ſelues of the name of Chryſte prayes to and worſhippes a pece of breade, and a ſuppe of wyne, for the ſonne of God whiche hath ſhed his bloud vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the croſſe for the redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all mankinde. O abomyna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble blaſphemye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the body &amp; bloude of the ſonne of God, that Lorde Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu Chryſt ſhuld be conuerted &amp; cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged into ſuche a wayke &amp; feble Idol yea into ſuche an Idoll whiche can neyther ſpeke nor fele, heare, ſee, go nor vnderſtande, yea whiche muſt vanyſhe awaye for age, with all the creatures vpon earth, whiche I ſaye muſt be kepped, caryed loked, of men lyke vnto the goddes of Babilon.<note place="margin">Baru. vii.</note>
            </p>
            <p>No my dearly beloued, no the ſone of God wyl not be lyke vnto y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buloſe prothens he wyll not nor he maye not be ſhute vp in a houſe
<pb facs="tcp:8679:35"/>
chamber, golde, nor ſyluer</p>
            <p>Rede I praye the .vii. and the .xvii. of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Actes. Eſay .lxvi.<note place="margin">Actes. vii. Eſay. lx.vi iii. Re. vii.</note> the heauen is his ſeat, and earth is his fotſtole.</p>
            <p>And Dauid ſayeth, wyll god in ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ded dwell wyth men on the earth beholde heauen, and heauen aboue all heauens do not conteyne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>, how muche leſſe the houſe whiche I haue buylded, all power is geuen vnto hym in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and earth, yea he hath ſet hym on his ryght hand in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thinges aboue all rewle and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer and myght,<note place="margin">ii. pata. vi Mat. xviii</note> and dominion in heauen and earth, he hath caſt all thinges vnder his bleſſed fete, he hath exalted hym one hye, and gyue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hym a name whiche is aboue at na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes that in the name of Ieſus,<note place="margin">Ephe. i philip. ii.</note> eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry kne ſhulde bone both thinges in heauen, and thinges in earth and al tonges ſhulde confeſſe that Ieſus Chryſte is the Lorde, he is aſcended
<pb facs="tcp:8679:36"/>
vp into heauen and ſhall not come agayne fleſhy vnto the tyme that he ſhall deuyde the ſhepe from the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes.<note place="margin">Math. xxv</note> Therefore I ſaye vnto you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne he can not be eaten with teth nor conciued in no belly. It is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible that this inwarde man whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is prophetable afore the lorde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he can eate or drynke any outwarde meate or drynke,<note place="margin">Externus externo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terno paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titurcibo.</note> namely breade and vyne as I haue declared before.</p>
            <p>But in the ryght ſupper of oure Lorde where we are congregated to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gether in the Lordes name wyth a fayth that is full of good workes, &amp; a loue vnfayned deſyringe to leue and dye accordinge to the Lordes pleaſure, there is delte out to my hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gre ſoule and thurſtye concience the inuiſyble fleſhe and bloude of oure ſauiour Ieſu Chryſt, and my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſeble man that is my ſoule recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth it and eateth it.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:8679:36"/>My dearly beloued this is the ryght table and cuppe of our lorde Ieſu Chryſte.<note place="margin">i. Cor. xi.</note> But the other whiche y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt parte of the world vſeth is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> table and cuppe of the deuel.<note place="margin">Cor. x.</note> I wold not ſayeth ſaynte Paule that you ſhulde be partakers of the table of deuilles.<note place="margin">i. Cor. x.</note> For lyke as theſe aboue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herſed haue the communion of the body and bloude of Chryſt, ſo hath lykewyſe the other the communion of the Antichryſt Idoll and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels table. And if it be ſo that we vſe and eate with them theyr ſacryfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce and breade, ſo declare we our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues to be wyth them one body and congregacion, for thorowe the ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge of the breade and drinking of the cuppe declare we how we are w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> them one breade and one bodye. O myſerable bodye that hathe neyther God, nor Chryſt, nor Spryte, nor Lyfe, nor Lyght, nor Worde, nor Truthe, nor Prayer, nor no maner
<pb facs="tcp:8679:37"/>
of promiſe. I ſpake here of the fleſh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye arrogant frewyllinge ſynners.</p>
            <p>But the ſymple that feares God ſeketh the truth and hath it not, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall the Lorde iudge accordinge to his godly wyl and mercye. O miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable body whych is euerlaſtyngly deade afore the eyes of the lorde, for in the is founde all the innocente blod that is ſhede vpon earth, from Abelles tyme vnto this daye,<note place="margin">Apo. xxii.xviii.</note> who dare apere before the ſtoole of God wyth ſuch an vngodly darke wrath full diſfigured Lecherous, bloodye bodye.</p>
            <p>¶O lord kepe and defende all thy poore ſeruauntes and true hartes from ſuche a bodye. But this lyes hide from the eyes of the world they are Dronken ſo ful with the wyne of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whore of Babilon. Thei know wel that the ſcripture wil haue vſed and holden a ſupper, but what ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, that is not knowen vnto them,
<pb facs="tcp:8679:37"/>
It is to the fleſhe to painfull ſtrayt and narow, that ſupper that oure ſauiour Chriſt haue lefte &amp; learned Therfore haue they choſen &amp; made themſelues a Supper whiche they receaue, with a beutyfull bodye and an vncleane ſoul of one which hath confeſſed them, which is more beaſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly and deuillyſh in all hys lyfe then they them ſelues are. Yea they haue auanſed this Diner ſo hye bicauſe of greate perell that the congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion muſt receaued but in one kynd namely breade and no wyne.</p>
            <p>But yf it were the Supper of our Lord, it muſt be miniſtred and vſed vnder both the kyndes. Therfore declare they it not to be the ryghte Supper of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt but it is and ſhal remayn the ryght Supper of Antichryſt, yea I ſaye they haue auanſed it ſo hie, that the ſelfe breade muſt be verye fleſh and the wyne very blood, yea that is the
<pb facs="tcp:8679:38"/>
vnfaythfull peoples nature bicauſe they do not knowe the inuiſeble god of heauen, nor the poure of the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tures. Therfore muſt they haue a viſible god, with whiche they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mytte fornication and vſe all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bomination agaynſt our ſauiour Ieſus Chryſt.</p>
            <p>Out of this vncleane ſtynking fountayne that is this learning, is flowed out all infidelyte and Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrye, which is vſed with this bread as lockynge it vp, caryeng it aboute leftyng it vp, prayeng to it, ſeaking it indyuers places, ſenſyng it, doing godly honour and reuerence to it, of the whiche ther is no tytle nor letter that can be founde in all the holye ſcryptures. Ye it is ſayde vnto this breade,<note place="margin">Exo. xxxiii</note> thou arte he whiche hathe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyuered vs vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Iebet of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe Lyke as the chyldren of Iſrael ſayd to the golden Calfe, this is he that hath delyuered vs out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lande of
<pb facs="tcp:8679:38"/>
Egypte. Awake vp and ſe the well afore you, ye that booſt and beare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of Chryſt, ye haue ſytt longe ynough in muche darknes, become wyſe, and gyue prayes &amp; glorye vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lorde God of heauen, to the intente that it come not vpon you, as it came vpon the chyldren of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſrael in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wyldernes bicauſe of there infidelyte, Idolatrye, and diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. All though that the Lorde de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyuered them out of the power of Pharo by his ſtronge hande and ſtraytched out arme,<note place="margin">ii Cor. x</note> what helped it them, verely nothing, lykewyſe it hel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pes vs nothing that we are redemed wyth the rede bloude of our ſauiour Ieſus Chryſte out of the deuels po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer and myght ſo farre forth as we make our ſelues boundmen againe thorowe our Infidelyte,<note place="margin">Hebre. iii. Iude. i.</note> Idolatrye diſobedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; fleſhly lyuing. Therd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they learne y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this ſelfe bread or ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t lyke as they name it, is geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and receaued for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> remiſſyon of ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſines,
<pb facs="tcp:8679:39"/>
my derely beloued wher chriſt Ieſus, and his holy worde is not, there is nothing,<note place="margin">vbi Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus non eſt ibi ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil ſanum.</note> but blyndnes, infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dilytye vayne hope dyſtruſt and an vnquyet conſiens,</p>
            <p>We knowe wel there muſt be a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatour for our ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes, but the ryght mediatoure Chryſt Ieſus we wyll not knowe. Therefore haue we elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and choſen out ſo many ſatiſfac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions for our ſynnes, ſo many that no man can thinke nor wryte, as Pardons holye water holy fyre, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſalte, holy breade, holy palme ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly waxe, holy bones, holye cottes, faſtinge, ſhryuinge Maſſinge,, pyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gramage with other abomynable baggage more, whiche is to long to reherſe, ye &amp; the dyner of Antychriſte and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> onely mediatour Ieſus chriſt wyll we not. Truly we are lyke vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a ſeyke febyll, fante wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded man y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> goeth and gyueth his mony to one y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is not expert in his ſcience whiche
<pb facs="tcp:8679:39"/>
can not gyue neyther holſome drink nor laye no good playſter, whiche deſtroyes more than he edifyes. And notwythſtandinge, there is declared vnto vs one expeart doctour which wyll neyther take gyftes nor rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, for he is of himſelfe rich inough and that he doth, he doth it of fren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dly fauoure and loue, ſeketh them at ther houſes, byndes vp there won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, healeth them and that frely, but we wyl not haue him, we haue more delyte in deſtruction, then in ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion. Who ſhal haue compaſſion or lamente ouer ſuche a ſeke man. It is in lyke caſe with this vnfaythfull generacion of man, they feyle many tymes greate paynes and ſmarte, &amp; runeth here and there to them, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che deſtroyeth more and more, wyth there falſe venemous medicines. It coſte them moche mony, they ſuffer moch ſmarte, and yet are they neuer made hole of ther diſeaces. And that
<pb facs="tcp:8679:40"/>
only euerlaſtynge riche perfect doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour and medecyne our ſauiour Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt which is ſo abundantlye declared vnto vs of all Patriarkes Prophetes, Angelles, Apoſtels, ye and of the father ſelfe, him wyll we not haue, which is come out of pure loue and fauour, to al them that are wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded and euel healed, and offers his ſeruice and hath brought wyth him a coſtlye precious ſalue that is good for al ſores, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is his precious rede blood that he for vs and for al the ſynnes of the worlde hath ſhede vpon the croſſe for our redemption, we wil not haue hym, we put him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye from vs with foote and hand, Touth and Nayl, ye we haue ſhote him awai from vs with our hornes and wyll not that Ieſus Chryſte ſhuld reygne ouer vs. Who ſhall haue compaſſion in the day of ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geaunce vpon our diſobedynt hard necked miſerable dampned ſoules
<pb facs="tcp:8679:40"/>
I ſay vnto you in Chriſte Ieſu be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue it, and you wyl rone where ye wyl, ſeake what meane, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye wyl, ye ſhall fynde no nother in all the hole ſcryptures, whyther ye be ſycke or hole ſtrong or wayke that ſhal pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect you afore the Lorde, ſaue onlye that that I haue declared vnto you that is Chryſte Ieſus or els ware al the holy ſcriptures falſe and ſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke lyes.</p>
            <p>Rede I praye you Eſay the Pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phete I am,<note place="margin">Eſay. xliii</note> euen I am the onli god and Lorde and beſydes me there is no Sauyour, I am he onlye that for my owne ſelues ſake do awaye thy offences and forget, thy ſinnes,<note place="margin">Eſay. liii.</note> he onlye hathe taken on hym out in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>firmytyes and borne our paynes ye y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord hath heped togither vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hym y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iniquiti of vs all,<note place="margin">Pſal. lxix.</note> he payd y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thing that he neuer had. The Angell ſayd to Ioſeph call his name Ieſus, for
<pb facs="tcp:8679:41"/>
he ſhall ſaue hys people from there ſynnes.<note place="margin">Math. i</note> This is my bloud the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ch is of the new Teſtament,<note place="margin">Mat. xxvi</note> that is ſhed for manye, for the remyſſion of ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes. Behold the la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be of god which taketh away the ſinnes of the world for he made him to be ſynne for,<note place="margin">ii. Cor. v Io. i.</note> vs whyche knew no ſynne, that we by hys meanes ſhulde be that ryghte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes whych before god is alowed he hath borne our ſynnes in his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tre,<note place="margin">i. Peter. ii i. Io. i Apoca. i. Heb. iii. i. Io. ii.</note> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> blood of Ieſus Chriſt his ſonne clenſeth vs from al ſynne He hath ſayth ſaint Iohn loued vs and waſſhed vs from our ſinnes in his owne blood which blood of the mediatour of the new Teſtament ſpeketh better then the blod of Abel</p>
            <p>If any man ſynne we haue an ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uocate with the father Ieſus Chriſt the ryghteous, and he it is that ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyneth grace for our ſynnes. Not for our ſynnes only, but alſo for the ſynnes of the hole worlde.</p>
            <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:8679:41"/>My dearly belowed brethren, yf there were any other aduocate or me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>diatour, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this Chryſt,<note place="margin">i. Timo. ii</note> how ſhame<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full had all the holye ſcryptures ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and howe pitefully had Sainte Paule deceaued vs wher he ſayeth, ther is one god &amp; one mediatoure be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twne good and man, euen the man Chryſt Ieſus which gaue hym ſelfe a raunſom for all men. Yf it be ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> throwe ſekenes any other meanes wherin thou doſt truſt to haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſinnes by let it be ſo lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſo holy ſo bewtiful as it wyl<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſaue onely that mediatour whiche is ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vs of god that is Chriſt Ieſu, ſo forſakes thou y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> death of our lord whiche he hath ſuffered for the, and thou denyeſt the moſt holyeſt and precious bloude that he hathe ſhede fore the.</p>
            <p>For all they that are not contente with this onely mediatour, but ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth after other, he curſeth godes
<pb facs="tcp:8679:42"/>
worde, he rentes in peces the goſpell of Ieſus chryſt, and vtterly denyeth that Chryſt is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ryght Meſſias lord and Mayſter, and ſauyour of the worlde, and that he is come from the father. My derely beloued in Chriſt Ieſu al thei y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſeke ani other ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge meanes wythout goddes worde o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſuche lamenteth the Lord,<note place="margin">Iere. ii.</note> by the mouth of the prophet Ieremye, my people haue done two euilles, they haue forſake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me, the well of the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of ſyfe, and digged them pittes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> can holde no water. This hathe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes bene the the ende of all falſe learnyng to forſake Chryſt Ieſus whoſe ryghteouſnes profeteth alon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly before the Lord, to the entent that we wold lyfte vp our owne ymagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacion, and ryghteouſnes to pray &amp; do reuerence vnto it as vnto a newe Chryſt. My dearly beloued here haue I breffly ſet you forth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> right learning of the ſupper of our Lorde Ieſus Chryſt how it ſhulde be my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred
<pb facs="tcp:8679:42"/>
in the congregacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God, accordinge to the Lordes word, here haue ye a confutacion of ſuttel per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaſyons &amp; argumentes of the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Antichryſt wherwyth they mayntayne ther meletyde otherwiſe called theyr dyner, for whiche cauſe muche ryghteous &amp; innocent bloude is ſhede wythout pitye or mercy in many places of the worlde, and all by the meanes of theſe ſpirytuall couniurers of Egypte. Exod. ix.<note place="margin">Exod. ix.</note> The Preſtes of the mountaines ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes of Ball and the prophetes Iezebell, the deſtroyers of the vyne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yearde of the Lorde,<note place="margin">ii. Reg. xix</note> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> defylers of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy earth. Sodome blind watchers &amp; dome dogges, the treaders downe of the ryght paſture and the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blers of the clere water,<note place="margin">Iere. xii. and .xiii. Eſa. v.vi. Eze. xxxiiii Math. vii Mat. xxiii Iohn. x.</note> falſe prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes &amp; grippi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g wolues Actes .xx. The deſtrouers of wedowes &amp; fatherles, theues and murtherers, enemyes of the croſſe of Chryſte whoſe ende
<pb facs="tcp:8679:43"/>
is danmacion whoſe god is there belly and glorye to there ſhame whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che are worldly mynded.<note place="margin">Philip. iii</note> They are falſe mayſters and fathers of ſectes hauing curſed children, welles with out watter,<note place="margin">ii. Pet. ii</note> dry cloudes wandrynge Starres, Trees without frut, at ga<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>theringe tyme wythered, twyſe dede and plucked vp by the totes, They are the raginge waues of the Sea, fomynge out there owne ſhame to whome is reſerued the myſt of Dar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kenes for euer,<note place="margin">Iude. i i. Io. ii</note> the ryght and true Antichriſtes,<note place="margin">Apoca. ix</note> theſe are the abomina<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble locuſtes whiche are come out of the botomeles pitte, to hurt al them, that haue not the marke of God in therefore hedes. Somma thoſe are they that are curſed and damned e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſtingly from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſence of god <note place="margin">Luke. vi.</note> excepte they repent and amende not that I Iudge theym that be farre from me for I know there ſtandes wrytten iudge not les thou be iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged,
<pb facs="tcp:8679:43"/>
condeme not les thou be conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, but they are iudged by the euer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>laſting worde of the Lord, the why<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che can neyther lye nor be diſſeaued like as our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt ſayeth,<note place="margin">Io. xii.</note> 
               <note place="margin">i Cor. v.vi</note> I iudge you not but it is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worde that I haue ſpoken that iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth you. Yf thou do the workes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Paule ſpeaketh of, thou ſhall not inheret the kyngdome of God. If thou do the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not ſo thou art not iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged of anye man, but of Goddes worde.</p>
            <p>Nowe my deare beloued lay theſe .ii. one agaynſt another, Gods lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge and mannes learnynge, the truth and the lye, Chryſt and Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſte, wey it, meſure it tell it, wyth the Lordes word, and I truſt in the Lorde that ye ſhall fynd nothynge, that I haue here declared, but the ryght true worde and wyll of oure ſauiour Ieſus chriſt.</p>
            <p>My dearly beloued be thankeful
<pb facs="tcp:8679:44"/>
vnto the almyghty maieſtie of god throw our Lorde Ieſus chriſt that it hath pleaſed him to let ſhyne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs the lyght of the holy Goſpell which hath be keped from vs ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny hundreth yere in the darke night of infidelitie.</p>
            <p>¶Therfore take it now vp as Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rymye ſayeth while it ſhyneth and tarye not leſt it be conuerted and chaunged into a dedlye darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, rede it right, it is godes word, amend your lyuing, ſerue your neyghbour w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al diligence, feare God and be obedient vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his holy word ſo ſhal y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> remayne in euerlaſting lyfe. Amen. ⸫</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thomas Lancaſter.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:8679:44"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>i. Cor. ii.</bibl>
                  <p>For another foundacion can no man laye than it that is laye, whiche is Ieſus Chryſt.</p>
                  <p>Prayſed be the Lorde God.</p>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Mark. viii</bibl>
                  <p>Whoſoeuer is aſhamed of me and of my wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des in this aduouterous and ſynfull generacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of him alſo ſhal y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſonne of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be a ſhamed whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he cometh in the glory of his father wyth the holy Aungelles.</p>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Ma. xxiiii</bibl>
                  <p>He that endureth to the ende the ſame ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be ſaued.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶Imprynded at Londone by Iohan Turke.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
